okay let's meditate
watch your
breath
e
e e
come to the Golden
Moon
e e
watch for
agitation
or
dness don't get
cocky mind is tied to the
object there's no other
object e
look outside the window the Blue Sky
broad Blue
Sky
e e
keep up your watchfulness don't lose
your
watchfulness e
and down to the
mountains e
and back to the Garden Room
ask your teacher to come sit with you
the golden sunlight
is pouring in touching your book
sit be content
satisfied feel like you could stay there
with your
teacher indefinitely feel their
presence don't have anywhere to go
there's nothing else to
do
e
e e
as we extend the sessions then it's more
likely that you'll have D lesser
agitation and not be able to catch
it br back your
effort bring back your effort
and and be vigilant
try to bring up a sense of nor sense of
enjoyment sense of
pleasure
e
e e
and slowly come back to this
room slowly open your eyes
so we were discussing
the you were on the subject of plus n
right you got to level
NBA uh still in the desire
room say single pointed
effortlessly uh sh J tbax
of shamata not quite shamata
yet then there are a couple of things
going on up here okay
and
uh 29 he's attaining uh shamata okay at
29 he's attaining
shamata uh but really I think all three
are happening around the same time 29 30
uh 30 is
uh Lu shinjang L shinjang bodily
shinjang okay
bodily Mastery accompanied
by uh sort of a bodily
high they they say Shing Bel
Shing Shin means
uh m a shinel means cotton sh means your
body feels light as
a so that's why he's flying in the
air and then he's sitting on the M
he's he's riding the elephant he's
controlling the elephant that's Sam Shin
Jang that's mental Shin Jang suit the
monk flying is
bodily uh Mastery and bodily High
pleasure in meditation and then sitting
on the elephant is me
Mastery of your meditation and mental
High pleasure and those are what
distinguish shamata from Level N9 okay
you have to go through
shinjang then I promised you
uh a pronic description of what was
going on okay and
um so uh
all that P says
[Music]
is say in your mind
okay it's kind of hard like she
something sh Show us at the she don't
N means uh place or condition Yen means
ban
okay uh Len means take
on and L means Pana okay so l l means
Pana that would cause you to take on a
bad condition okay Prana that would
cause you to take on a bad condition
uh and then he
says
sha that is uh pacified or they are put
to rest okay
Shanti okay they are put to rest so the
the pranas in the body that would cause
you to take on
an a negative condition are put to rest
and that triggers shinan okay so
something's happening to certain Pras in
your
body between level 9 and and real
shamata so somehow you have to affect
some change in subtle Pras in your body
between level 9 and Shino okay so what
then he doesn't really much go on he
just he doesn't describe that much so
what I did was
uh I used our database our database
means uh we have a project called
acip for 20 4 years
now and uh they
find uh rare text there were
5,000 libraries in Tibet were destroyed
during the cultural
revolution uh so very few texts were
left and
um we found uh huge repositories of Tex
in Japan and Russia and
Mongolia there's also some in be
and uh still some in
Tibet so anyway any any country where
and some in India so any country where
we could get a scan or a copy of a text
we did and that's
about in Russia we we spent 14 years in
the library there and cataloged
130,000 texts and we still haven't
scanned those we didn't have time yet to
scan them so that we're we've done about
a million pages and that's about 5% of
what we have to do so I figure another
150 years
in depending on funding okay uh but what
it means is just the million pages that
we have put in already which are in my
computer uh and which are free online
okay so we we we get we put them free
online uh you can go in and look
up L and get a better description of it
you can go through 2 and a half thousand
years of literature and and see how it
developed the idea of that special kind
of product so this is kind of what I
spend a lot of my time doing you know I
go dig for a better explanation and my
hope is that we could
uh a lot of the ancient texts are
corrupt and uh we're slowly cleaning
them
up several thousand years of corruption
are cleaning up and then uh translate
them teach people to translate them and
then teach them like this make them
practical people can use them and then
uh
do secondary works like The Diamond
Cutter business work book or something
like that so that's one Sutra out of
200,000 you know and 3 million people
are using that so my my hope is that
your
generation you know you
could be working on you could take a
teaching like
this uh either in Tibetan or in English
and then you could regurgitate it for
your own Pierce you know that you could
recast it in Paris or wherever you live
uh and you could turn it into your own
language and you could adjust it for
your own friends or your your own Circle
and then it
would those ancient Classics could
become uh what do you call accessible to
to everybody in the modern world so you
have to reinterpret what I'm
doing and then you have to present it in
your own context maybe you teach in a
yoga class or you know maybe you teach a
small Dharma group or maybe
you teach business people or whatever in
your own country and in your own way you
you adjust it okay so but my idea is you
go
from the original sources
very carefully and then you synthesize
and modify and make it accessible to
Modern people I imagine that in the end
there would be a lot of little videos or
cartoons or the best explanation of
quantum physics I ever saw was a a
little
cartoon uh you know so maybe there could
be a cartoon on the nine levels or
something I don't know or or a drama I
don't know so you have to my My Hope Is
that based on those ancient Classics we
you know we we take an idea like these
subtle
pranas that that throw you into high
pleasure during meditation and then you
you work on that maybe you develop a
yoga series for those or you know like
that okay so anyway I went to a bunch of
quite old texts and over a history over
a period of a couple thousand years and
I thought I would just read you
selections that explain that kind of
pra and then you get a feeling for what
acip is doing you know what they're
there mostly Refugee women and they're
sitting there typing all day for 24
years now and uh now you can see how we
use it okay so here's the first one uh
this is from a text by the third Pion
llama it's called tan which means uh he
students were asking him
questions and these are his
replies so
uh he's explaining a certain famous
eight lines of
Praise which go
M
okay uh some of you may
know okay and uh he says MJ MJ means
the tendency of the mind to go dark
mukba means fog MJ means the tendency of
the mind to go dark R means the tendency
of the mind to go a little bit too hyper
okay and Mong means the tendency of the
mind to just block
out and get really stupid okay
Mong means there's a certain
Angel uh who helps us over overcome
those three Tendencies of the mind he's
explaining a very special almost a
mantra and he's explaining those that
line you know you help us
overcome
all uh
confusion
hyperness and darkness of the mind and
then he says it's because she has the
capacity
when she has the capacity to help you
stop
your L okay so there's already just one
little piece of information for people
who are familiar with that other
practice um she has she's able to help
you stop
those like hyper mind hyper busy mind or
dull mind or dark mind she has the
capacity to stop those because nangu
means within she's able to reach in
within you
and and shut down those subtle winds
which are causing that which are called
Prana of of taking on a bad condition
okay that's
all then he
says okay and if you don't know what
that means you're not supposed to okay
uh then we go to a this is Chun uh with
one of the cha R this is a cinti cinti
means he gave a teaching on the
L I believe sometime in the 18th century
and uh and here's his explanation okay
that this is kind of long and I'm just
going to take it through all of them cuz
I enjoy them I think the tradition our
lineage's tradition is when you hit a
tough spot like L you stop and you spend
half a day on it you know I mean it's
our it's our tradition it's on copian
tradition that when you get to something
you don't understand you don't skip it
you stop until you understand it and
maybe until you understand it better
than rest of the stuff that's just its
own C of thing so here we
[Music]
go the ninth level of
meditation is an
approximate and it is true that at that
time you do have a very little touch of
shinjang okay even at level 9 you have a
subtle means a very tiny sliver you have
a
sliver of shin
okay and then slowly that shinjang
begins to increase in in in slow gradual
stages it begins to increase you go
and because of
that because of that you are able to put
to rest
the the Pras which make you take on bad
States and then he describes them in a
very classical way so if you want to
know what those pranas do those little
nasty we can call them little nasty Pras
okay how about that little nasty p Us by
the way he's going to talk about where
they are how they circulate how to shut
them down okay but their function is
classically described in these
words when those subtle nasty pranas are
flowing you are unable
to what do you call
it you are unable
to inspire yourself to goodness okay you
are unable
to move yourself to
goodness when those little nasty pranas
are moving you find yourself unable
to what you call Move Yourself to to do
goodness so that's pretty much their
function okay then she uh if you get
shinjang you can put those to rest sh
sh then you get mental Shin okay so he's
saying you get
mental uh Mastery first
mental Shin Jang comes first okay
fluency or Mastery or whatever you want
to call it accompanied by high
PL the first the mental one comes day
two we're describing what's happening to
you between level 9 and Sham okay it's
pretty heavy stuff head he stuff okay
day due to
that the little good guy Pras begin to
circulate and they their name it toban
is
L okay
L A lot of people in the room know the
word L because it's the it's the word
used for a tantric Retreat a tantric
Mantra retreat in Tibet it's called Lum
but it's called Lum because that's an
abbreviation to the word Luma Luma means
fit for Duty you know fit for Duty ready
to do what you're supposed to be doing
okay lay
rule like if you're in the military and
you've trained them people well you know
they know weapons they know running they
know everything they're called L room
they're fit for Duty they're like ready
to go ready to search
l so tantic Retreats are called laser
because they make you fit for higher
things okay they prepare you they make
you ready for higher
things uh but the the subtle winds which
move in the body between level 9 and
shamata that bring on shamata are called
L the Pras of L A proness of readiness
l means they begin to circulate
throughout the
body uh and because of that Lon tell me
uh
you you become free of negative states
of body physical negative States
okay
okay you get bodily shinjang which is up
here the guy flying right you get bodily
shinjang uh
Bel where is that belar Yang Yang means
light belar means cotton light as a
cotton ball but in English we say light
as a feather right you feel like your
body's
flying or rising up off your meditation
okay
to due to
that
uh you get a rush of pleasure through
your body okay you get rushes of
pleasure coming through your
body so if you
notice I I want to it's sort of a
circular thing okay first you overcome
uh nasty
Pras okay um due to the subtle increase
of shinan you overcome nasty
Pros uh they cause a mental
shinan okay they trigger certain Good
Winds passing through your
body and then
uh they
trigger uh a freedom
from nasty winds right and then bodily
you feel light and then because of that
you
feel a physical pleasure okay so he's
trying to describe this thing where it
starts in the mind something happens in
the mind and that affects the nasty
winds that causes Good Winds to flow
that causes the body to feel light and
that causes a pleasure in the body
remember yesterday we said first to get
the mental shinjang with it then that
brings on the bodily shinjang that
brings on the pleasure of the bodily
shin and that brings on the pleasure of
the mental sh okay so you
have uh what was it mental
Mastery due to a change in the pros
becomes physical Mastery which brings on
a physical Bliss which in turn creates a
mental Bliss
okay mental physical physical mental
okay mental physical physical
mental
try and because of the pleasure you feel
in your body after it got light okay
shinjang made it light then came on a
sensation of pleasure
okay and then because your body feels so
good you get mental pleasure okay so to
trace it backwards mental pleasure is
triggered by physical pleasure is
triggered by physical adeptness is
triggered by mental adeptness okay like
that
right anyway you feel physically and
mentally cool all
right to this is interesting okay right
after you get the physical Sensation
that you feel like you could fly by the
way I
mean in
practice this in infects your whole day
right if you reach a physical Shin Jang
during your sessions then all day weird
stuff will be happening to you okay like
the body becomes very
straight uh you're always sitting up
straight you
feel pleasure in sitting up straight
always think of the military acad ofy
these guys required to sit on the front
half of the chair up straight and that's
chicly that's a very smart thing to do
uh it's a very uh it would work to make
the mind more clear okay uh
so when you reach states of shin Jang
you'll know it because physically you'll
feel better and that's where yoga helps
a lot okay yoga strengthens the body
yoga opens the channels and then you'll
you'll just find yourself going into
these
little patches during the day of like
rushes and
uh straight upness straight uprightness
something like that you're always
straight up right like that you might
also by the way it doesn't say it here
but you
also might find yourself at these states
getting into Keva kumaka which is the
spontaneous uh supension of the breath
you during these stages of your practice
level 9 and around there you might start
finding that you your breath stops
spontaneously for 5 6 10 15 minutes okay
you don't breathe for 10 or 15 minutes
and you're just not aware of it really
like you're sitting in a library or
something and and you're you're in a
state sort of semi meditation and and
then you realize you haven't breathed
for 10 minutes something like that okay
um Shin to right after you get the
feeling of physical shinjang right which
is where your body feels
like uh or or
straight not talk to by the way that
would also mean that if your posture is
bad all the time it's probably really
hurting your meditation if you got close
to level nine and your posture was
always stooped over then you'd have
trouble moving on to shamata okay so I
mean just yogis are
always okay I find ballet house a lot or
some kind of what do you call it
something that works on your
alignment talk
to uh you begin to get uh
let me
see you begin to get a little too
high okay these are very subtle these
are very subtle like we like
this okay and you know you're like oh my
body feels like cotton and then your
mind goes a little tiny bit too high
Y and that blocks the shamata slightly
okay that that obstructs the shamata you
you get a physical Rush then you get a
corresponding over mental Rush mental
over Rush slight very very subtle and
then uh it it sort of prevents you from
from the shamata which is about 3
seconds away
okay then that that high resides sorry
what do you call it when a wave uh a
wave uh
yeah when a wave crashes and then it
settles
uh yeah E is good that's good E is good
that uh I never would have thought of
that no matter how much you okay
uh the the highness the mental highness
ABS slightly okay this is cool this
whole process is cool somebody should
translate this
uh
uh then you go into
a a state where the
mind uh is starting
to sink into the object okay the mind
starts to sink into the object okay
and then the Mind continues to melt into
the object and then uh you get a
corresponding what do you call it your
shinjang becomes
imperturbable okay shinan
becomes right AIA it becomes unmovable
in that moment where I'm going to
cry in that
moment you achieve sh that's sham you
just hit shamata after all these days of
this stupid
chart
okay number 28 okay you hit sham
you hit sh that's cool the last few
seconds he's describing the last few
seconds you get you get a rush you get a
little too high it EVS a bit and you hit
shamata okay you hit
sham and it's all
pronic which is why we're doing yoga
okay
and but then don't forget he said
something
so you should say now it's time to say
in your head
something
something me man okay very very
important this is the meditative
platform required to see emptiness
directly okay it's the it's the special
rifle scope the special model these
special production series that you must
get to to see emptiness directly you can
think of meditation as a huge
spectrum of of mental States we can take
a meditation like going from I don't
know what is it red to Yellow like
thousands of colors of meditation only
one of those slices is the one you need
to see emptiness dire and this is it
okay you got to be a to get to that one
tiny slice of meditation which will
enable you to see emptiness directly and
it's only
that okay so we got to talk about what's
that right we'll do it maybe we'll do it
in a little bit we'll do it today
sometime
[Music]
okay anyway s means J okay s means s is
one of the words for meditation
but it specifically refers to
the
causal form realm meditation what does
that mean the meditation that if you
spend a lot of time in it in this life
and then you died you would be born into
that form realm okay so it's called form
realm meditation not because you're in
the form realm but because if you did it
a lot in this life and then you died you
would be born into that temporary
Paradise okay so that State of Mind in
itself if you just left it it that it's
not so useful it's just a tool okay it's
just a tool it's a deep state of
meditation mentally you are out of the
desire real for the first time in your
life okay mentally you are you are no
longer in the desire realm meaning if
some boy came up and kissed you or
somebody put french fries in front of
your nose you're you're beyond it okay
your mind is past that okay that's
important okay and we'll talk more about
it N means uh we'll talk more I'm going
to do that later
anyway you achieve a
shamata which is included within the
formal which is part and parcel of the
formal in a causal sense
this type of sham is both an inner and
an
outer meditative
capacity if you undertake this level of
concentration combined with a view of
emptiness so you sense that we're about
to combine the two flows of teaching of
this Retreat right okay here it comes
if your mind is imbued with the correct
view of that there's no nit right and if
you truly seek for
Freedom uh if you if your mind is full
of compassion for other beings and you
want to save the world from suffering
take
CH then there shamata becomes
Mah then this shamata becomes the State
of Mind of those who wish to save the
world
okay otherwise it's just a neutral thing
right it's just a state of concentration
if at those moments why do they say
imbued with that why do they say imbued
with that uh yeah as you get close to a
direct perception of emptiness you can't
think about saving the world cuz that's
not
emptiness why well simply that's a
positive thing and Emptiness is an
absence of something those two states a
human mind a non- enlightened mind
cannot concentrate on an absence and a
presence at the same time not possible
an enlightened mind can okay but a human
mind a non- enlightened human mind
cannot cannot so they they say you are
close to seeing emptiness directly or
you seeing emptiness directly
you can't feel compassion at that time
because compassion
is is a positive thing it's not a
absence of
something but your mind can be imbued
with it your mind can be soaked in that
compassion and then you go into the
direct perception of emptiness or you go
into that shamata and that's mahay
that's higher that's a practice of bodh
we want to save the world okay all
right dang
[Music]
and
and and based on that State of Mind
powerful
shamata uh focused on Ultimate Reality
right and imbued with love for
others because of
that you reach what's called okay say
don't say don't say and
sayong okay
Tong is V Tong is pasana
okay
pasana and in the southern Asia Burma
Thailand Sri Lanka it got corrupted to
vasana it got corrupted to Vias vasana
is sweeping China right now it's not
even gu vasana
it's just some I don't know who made it
not it's all everybody says I'm doing
Papas or you say what is it no I'm not
quite sure but
anyway
uh theas is a corruption
ofan uh it doesn't refer to the Sham
which is the way it is I would learn
from the
D forced me and all the other students
in D Salo when I was there to go study
with ginki and we did and it it's
fantastic but anyway he what he calls
vasana is really
sham okay and then
theana is to use the shamata to see
emptiness that's Viana okay and then our
goal is to
link sh okay you
use high state of
meditation to see emptiness directly
okay and then that's that's the Union
of shamata which you could call
sometimes I call it quietude or what is
it I
forget all those kind of
words some other word I don't
remember it means quiet she name means
staying in a quiet
State uh you can call it quietude or
something like that what did he call it
here uh this
transl that was
me yeah quietude here I put quietude
okay uh and in Viana you can call it
Insight okay VI means special or
extraordinary Pasha means to
see so bana means extraordinary inside
okay
bana that combination of shamata and
Viana uh gome if you if you practice
that and then he's done that's his
description of the N lamb okay those bad
guy Pros okay he says if you can
join Insight with a deep capacity for
meditation
then you will be freed from the chains
of the two obstructions
okay and shid okay and Sh what are the
two
obstructions one is all the negative
emotions that prevent you from achieving
Nirvana
okay and one is the very very subtle
energies in in your being which prevent
you from achieving omniscience okay
omnition we say in Buddhism that you can
achieve omniscience but not
omnipotence at least not in the normal
sense of
the okay so omniscience means you can
bring your mind to a a place where you
can see all things in all
times positive and negative at the same
time okay you
can and long before that you can open
your mind your heart chakra right to a
place where you can
observe the future 500 years out you can
observe other people's minds thinking
about
you like I don't know
anyway it would be pretty weird right if
you knew exactly what people were
thinking especially about you uh if you
could hear their thoughts
directly uh and then
uh you can see all the places in the
world at the same time see the human
mind under the influence of
shamata
andana has the capacity to see
everything in the world at the same time
your mind already has that capacity it's
probably you could say a lot of Tibetan
traditions and I technically it may not
be true but I like it uh is that that's
your natural state your natural state is
that you're capable of you can say that
you can even say that your natural state
is that you can see all things in all
times you could watch everybody in the
world cooking breakfast right
now or going to bed you see at the same
time
your mind your the natural capacity of
your mind is that your your mind
naturally has that capacity but it is J
Jaa means it's it's blocked from that
capacity if you can
reach this
guy uh sitting on the elephant shamata
combined with Viana then you
can you can reach that capacity you can
unveil that capacity and then you would
return to to your natural capacity which
is the capacity to see all things in all
times and that makes you
useful no I mean I'm always looking for
people to help me with projects you know
like I meet somebody they say I say how
are you they say fine I say you know I
say how's the retreat going they say I'm
having a terrible time I want to talk to
you about my meditation then I said do
you know accounting you know
so but somebody who can see everything
now that's
useful
all like what's the lottery numbers for
next week in Utah you know and stuff
like that
okay
fundraising all right
[Laughter]
uh okay let's know one more time and
then we're not done with L okay we're
not done with those subtle Pros we got
to talk about where they flow what they
feel
like what it feels like when you shut
them
down watch your breath
please
e
e e
come to the golden
MO
e
e e
see this guy
take sustenance
from the calm and the quiet
you mind leaves bring it
back e
come down to the mountains in the valley
covered in
sunlight wide spreading
I'm into the golden
room sit with your
teacher fa in Golden Light
feel their hands on your
heads the touch of their hands is a
single point of
meditation just focus on the touch it's
the only thing in the world that
[Music]
matters stay there deeply
contented just for a few
minutes
e
e e
and slowly come back to this
one relax
[Music]
sh of
sh
[Music]